I mean, come on. We all love Abraham
Lincoln now, but here's where I tell you
that his election in 1860 was all kinds
of nasty because his victory led the
United States right smack down the road
to civil war. And I reckon we ought to
talk about it. So, if you're ready to
get them brain cows milk secession
style, let's get to it. Okay, now I
mentioned in the last video that the
second party system had died out by
1854. And by the 1860 election, it was
the Democrats competing with the brand
spanking new Republican party. And
remember that these parties were now
altogether sectional parties, which
means that Republicans represented the
North while the Democrats represented
the South. In other words, they were
like that kid who refuses to eat his
dinner if any part of his food is
touching any other part of his food. And
the same goes with these parties. The
political plate was divided. And as for
the peas and mashed potatoes, uh, no
touching. Now, the Republicans were a
party formed by a coalition of
anti-slavery wigs and free soilers. And
that meant that the Republicans were
indeed the anti-slavery party, but the
free soil emphasis meant that they were
only opposed to the expansion of slavery
into the western territories. So
Republicans made it abundantly clear
that they would not seek to outlaw or
diminish slavery in the states where it
already existed. And so for the election
of 1860, the Republicans chose Illinois
Senator Abraham Lincoln as their
candidate, who had gained notoriety
during the 1854 congressional election
by debating Steven Douglas on the merits
of slavery and popular sovereignty.
Anyway, the point is the Republican
party going into this election was
united behind one gangly bearded giant,
but it was not so with the Democrats.
But before I tell you about that hot
mess, let me just quickly mention that
if you want to get an A in your class
and a five on your exam in May, that you
might want to check out my A Push
Heimler review guide. It's got
everything you need to study as fast as
possible, and that link is in the
description below. Anyway, the Democrats
broke into waring factions leading up to
this election, which basically assured
their electoral defeat. So, northern
Democrats nominated Steven Douglas as
their candidate and he ran on a popular
sovereignty platform. And then the
southern Democrats nominated the sitting
vice president, John Breenri. And then a
faction of southern wigs formed the
Constitutional Union Party and nominated
Tennessee Senator John Bell, who really
offered no solution to the slavery
problem. And long story short, Lincoln
won the crap out of the election. But
here's the thing to remember. He won
without gaining a single electoral vote
from the South. Like, not one. I mean,
part of the reason Lincoln won so
handily was that the Democrats split the
electoral votes between three
candidates, as you can see here. But
look, even if the Democrats had put
forward a single candidate, Lincoln
still would have won in a landslide. He
got 180 electoral votes, while the
various other candidates won a combined
total of 123. And the Republicans
certainly owed another part of that
victory to the recent admission of
Minnesota and Oregon to the Union in
1858 and 1859, respectively. Both
entered as free states, which meant that
free states now outnumbered slave states
18 to 15. But even more than that, the
free states in the north had far bigger
populations than the slave states in the
south. So, can you begin to see from the
perspective of the South why this
election convinced them that they no
longer had a home in the United States?
Like, it became abundantly clear that
they no longer had any chance to protect
their interest in a political system
they could never again control. And so,
the direct result of that election was
that at long last, the South decided
that the slavery question would be
answered not by compromise, but rather
by divorce. Now, as a free soil
advocate, Lincoln made absolutely clear
that he believed that he had no
constitutional authority to eradicate
slavery where it already existed. All he
aimed to do was prevent it from
spreading westward. But first of all,
Southerners just didn't believe it. And
that mistrust was deepened by events
like John Brown's raid on Harper's Ferry
and the popularity of books like Uncle
Tom's Cabin, which branded slavery as an
evil institution. And then second, as I
mentioned before, from the southern
perspective, the only hope of keeping
slavery alive was to expand westward.
like even if it was allowed to remain in
all the southern states, they just
discovered in no uncertain terms in the
presidential election that their
political efficacy had been shattered.
And so by December of 1860, the South
Carolina legislature drafted its formal
articles of secession and broke from the
United States. They argued that the
Republican party had engineered the
election and gave power to a man hostile
to slavery. And so in their articles of
secession, South Carolina gave two
distinct but related reasons for their
departure. First, they believe that the
North's intent was to wage a war against
slavery until it shall cease throughout
the United States. And then second, if
that happened, the equal rights of the
states will be lost. So South Carolina
seceded from the Union in order to
protect slavery, which they believed was
their constitutional right. And then
only a few months later, six other
states followed South Carolina's lead
and seceded as well. You had
Mississippi, Florida, Alabama, Georgia,
Louisiana, and Texas. And then by June
of 1861, Virginia, Arkansas, North
Carolina, and Tennessee voted to secede
as well. and altogether they formed the
Confederate States of America. Now all
of the seceding states wrote articles of
secession and in every last one of them
they acknowledged that their
justification for separating was to
protect slavery and uphold their rights
as states. Now to be clear in every
state that seceded there were fierce
debates over whether they should break
from the Union or continue to work
toward compromise. But ultimately they
decided that secession was the only
possibility. Okay. So at that point the
Confederacy ratified a new constitution
that corrected what they viewed as two
egregious errors of the United States
Constitution. First, unlike the United
States, the Confederacy was to be a
Christian nation. And to that end, the
preamble invokes the favor and guidance
of Almighty God. Second, the Confederate
Constitution made very clear provisions
for the legality and perpetual
protection of slavery in the new
country. So once that was done, they
elected Jefferson Davis as the president
and his vice president was Alexander
Stevens. Now, I know for some people
it's controversial of me to claim that
the South seceded to protect slavery. It
was about states rights and you know it,
son. Well, then I'm really confused
because Alexander Stevens in his
cornerstone speech made the foundation
and purpose of this new nation
absolutely clear. He said that the
stupid United States government was
founded on the lame idea of racial
equality. But he goes on, "Our new
government is founded upon exactly the
opposite idea. Its foundations are laid.
Its cornerstone rests upon the great
truth that the negro is not equal to the
white man. That slavery, subordination
to the superior race, is his natural and
normal condition. This our new
government is the first in the history
of the world." based upon this great
physical, philosophical, and moral
truth. So make of that what you will.
Regardless, the United States was now
entirely broken apart, and Lincoln, in
no mood to abide such an
unconstitutional act by the South,
started preparing for the war to come.
And that is where we're going to pick up
in the next video. Well, okay, you can
click here to watch my other videos for
unit 5, or you can click here to grab my
A push Himler review guide, which has
everything you need to get an A in your
class and a five on your exam in May.
I'm glad you came around, and I'll catch
you on the flip-flop. Pameler out.